welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
hello everybody and welcome to the stoah
stoah is a digital campfire where we
gathered to go here in dialogue at the
knife's edge of what matters most my
name is Raven and I will be your host
for the evening and today we have the
fourth session of a series that we've
been doing with Sam Oh Borgia called
live players so with that I'll just tell
you the structure we're gonna have him
speak for about 15 to 20 minutes and
then we'll move over to a question and
answer period which I will be emceeing
so you can go ahead and drop any
questions or comments you may have in
the chat and then we'll get to them
during the question and answer period
with that Sam oh go ahead and take it
away I think well the interesting
question that's on a lot of people's
minds is decline and how do you deal
with decline what does it mean for a
society to be in decline what are the
options for life in a world where
basically you know the institutional
opportunities that you might have grown
up expecting are just not there this I
think is a question that's been asked
many times in history the standard
rebuke to the idea that things could be
worse is that Socrates and Plato were
already complaining about the youth
being corrupted by the art of reading
how reading his destroyed memory and how
the youth are misbehaving what dismisses
however is that there could be
complaints of this type you know
everything is going to hell in a
handbasket or several centuries
throughout history and it will be
completely accurate if you imagine a
wave a sine wave there are samples of
the wave where it's going down every few
centuries right so such complaints could
be completely justified I think usually
there's a tendency to overestimate how
much cultural change transformation and
growth is a sign of decline because of
this I can to not focus so much on
direct observations of cultural norms
oftentimes new social technologies can
obsolete
all social technologies a very strong
clan structure where everyone's taking
care of kin
kinfolk primarily can be easily replaced
with a different more urbanized society
and morally you might see the
urbanization and the arising of a
national consciousness rather than a
tribal consciousness is the climb but
actually it's just a displacement of one
social technology for another perhaps
one with some negatives and downsides
that the old one didn't have but in
inevitably also strengths because you
know the sort of nation-state style
approach fields stronger armies has
larger economies easily defeats tribal
societies this difficulty of
ascertaining when a social technology
Falls away because it's no longer used
or because you know it's just merely
gone into disrepair the difficulty of
separating those two caused me to not
really pay that much attention to some
of the stuff that commentators like you
know given in his book the decline of
the Roman Empire might tend to focus on
I think I prefer to look at things that
are in the material space so urban
population centers either having
stagnant population sizes or dropping
population sizes economic
underperformance increased unrest and so
on like these kind of things these are
more objective now even for something
like unrest and the presence of violence
can be misleading many very successful
very expansionary functional societies
can be very violent right you know if
you someone looked at the Wild West in
America's history one can perhaps have
moral objections to it one can note the
high degree of violence and anarchic
state and fighting and so on but if you
called that a dissolution of social ties
a decline a collapse a social unrest
you're really not tracking reality
properly this is actually a very
expansion airy frontier culture it's
producing massive amounts of growth
arguably when the history books are
written the
see California which is in a way the
most extreme product of this post
frontier expansion of the 19th century
as being the most influential state of
the early 21st century us where it's
very clear that Western centers of power
and culture within the United States are
coming too slowly
suppliant Eastern centers so in the very
long run I think New York will be
eclipsed by either Seattle or San
Francisco so violence disorder this kind
of stuff it's again more objective than
cultural observations but still not
quite real I think therefore the
population numbers are an interesting
proxy the most demands technologies are
a good proxy the presence or you know
absence of material production is a
proxy almost always societies really
don't voluntarily cut back consumption
what usually happens is that their
economizing on some limit now the
resources they're exhausting might be
quite abstract it might be similar to
the guarantee in civilization in modern
day Libya with a it's the only case I
know of where they actually ran out of
you know water right they had fossil
water this means water that's not part
of the water cycle they were tapping it
through wells and eventually they ran
out of that water that had been trapped
underneath even the earth for millions
of years
unable to irrigate their population
dropped eventually you know Roman
punitive expeditions couldn't be
repulsed and the civilization vanished
from the world now some of the members
of it obviously migrated to other parts
a lot of them just you know died or
perished in these these natural
circumstances of the social disorder
that followed this decline sort of focus
you know this very concrete resource
like running out of water it's rarely
that concrete it's a more abstract
resource for example you could have a
society that seems very economically
productive but is actually in the course
of economic growth undermining the
preconditions for the high social the
high
environment of social trust which
existed which in the first place allowed
the low friction on business
transactions the respect for creativity
the sort of good relations between
labour and capital and so on and you
could see a total breakdown there you
know the aftermath of the Bolshevik
Revolution is interesting to study but
it's very clear that when the Bolshevik
Revolution happened there was some sort
of contradiction or inability some kind
of resource was exhausted however
abstract that resource might be in
Czarist Russia that prevented zahra
structure for simply continuing
industrialization and perhaps slowly or
concretely you know in incremental steps
or in piecemeal steps changing their
social system to account for this
resource in an important way social
reforms are always undertaken it's only
a question of how how quality' you know
how high-quality those social
interventions will be so a period of
decline could have many many attempts at
reform the Roman Empire in the reign of
Diocletian actually solved very
extensive socio-economic reforms the
introduction of what later might be
called serfdom was done in the fourth
century AD so what they did was because
of social unrest and so on they simply
issued a law you know if you are if your
father is a carpenter then you are a
carpenter it is illegal to change your
profession
this was meant as a social stabilization
measure instead of having guilds all
over the place with granted monopolies
they just issued monopolies to basically
the whole economy insofar as these
things were respected it was the
flash-freeze the state of the economy as
it exists now of course you might say
flash-freezing the economy that sounds
very familiar
didn't we just try to do this when we're
giving companies lots and lots of money
to keep the books as they are we're
actually saying no you are not allowed
to shift into a new form you are not
allowed to do something else we are in
fact paying you and requiring you to try
to do the same thing you were doing
before even if it doesn't make sense
No you know I think there should be a
real structural change in the economy in
response to : that I think will not
happen the high degree of social unrest
that we're experiencing it might produce
positive social reform or it might not I
think we have to understand that the
Civic enthusiasm and level of
responsibility right now is lower than
it once was in the United States as is
the optimism towards actually resolving
some of the most pressing and very real
social issues that have always been
there with the slowed economy and with
Millennials and Zoomers being the
poorest generations in their age bracket
ever so if you look at a graph of how
much property how much wealth does each
generation own through the course of
their lifetime and you plot the
generations right so as they acquire
more wealth as they're richer and richer
Millennials go at the bottom of that
graph I'll link it after the lecture and
I think Zoomers will do even worse so
the economic game's not viable The
Consumerist game is not viable the
ideological fight with the Soviet Union
is long gone the ideological fight with
you know Communist China is much more
complex the level of analysis of
Communist China or modern-day China
let's just say it is modern right if you
call it communist do you try to force it
in this Cold War mentality you're both
missing things and in other ways you're
correct it is based on the theoretical
basis of Marxism and Leninism
and to a much lesser extent Maoism
nihilism has been arguably significantly
deprecated in modern-day China however I
think we just understand it way lests in
1950s and 1960s the West can be seen as
like very strongly anti-communist but
almost all of America's intellectual
elites understood what Marxism is today
I think it almost no one understood
understands what Marxism is let alone
what you know socialism with Chinese
characteristics might be where our vast
efforts to try to translate these big
ideological tomes where are these
investigations of how do positions
change within the Communist Party
America should be following Chinese
internal politics in his
much detail and as closely as the
British right now follow American
internal politics but because we don't
we don't really understand the outside
world and because we don't really
understand the outside world I really
doubt that there'll be a successful
response there so going through it all
these signs seem to be there which is
not to say that is not perhaps on social
progress and it's not to say that
there's not some material progress what
it is saying is that the institutions
that I see around us are clearly running
out of resources they're not running out
of water
we definitely are not running out of oil
but there is some constraint that we've
hit and I want to hear people's opinion
as to what that constraint is of course
if anyone wants to serves challenge does
produce been carryin arguments I'm very
happy to talk about say this kind of
like Amelia test view where things are
getting better but I'm just predicating
this conversation on the yes we know
what the Klein looks like we see what
it's like and then after a few questions
maybe I'll say a bit about historical
examples of successful reef foundings
right decline is not necessary terminal
you could easily have again a sine wave
or even an oscillating curve of progress
if you could come up with a
quantification that was worthwhile at
all for progress that people might value
actually thank you so we will now be
moving on to the question and answer
period of the session so if people have
questions statements propositions you
can go ahead and drop them into the chat
if you don't want to speak on behalf of
your question you can just indicate to
me that you want me to read it and I'll
go ahead and read it on your behalf and
I guess samo I was just gonna ask you
initially so even before we kind of saw
all this social unrest there's been a
lot of critique of the calcification of
institutions tyler cohen calls this the
great stagnation you know eric weinstein
talks about it as as like the disc the
distributed idea suppression complex is
there a kind of something necessary or
maybe helpful about a kind of soft
collapse that allows for these
institutional structures to be kind of
undermined to allow for the possibility
of something to arise that kind of
addresses some of the systemic or
institutional calcification that we've
been seeing maybe since the seventies
but maybe even just the 20th century in
general either definitely benefits right
there are some benefits it seems to me
that with regard to pacification right
the question is well okay we've reduced
violence but have we in the process
crippled human nature too much right
there's the classical there's the
classical nineteenth-century critique
where you know I forget what this might
be shutting our my Benita were proposes
that you know how do you make an animal
how do you domesticate an animal and he
goes through the behavioral
characteristics of a domesticated animal
and notes that all of those are also the
behavioral characteristics of a wild
animal and the wild animal is feeling
sick when they're feeling ill and
proposes likewise it is with man right
man is inhumanity not just male this the
sort of perspective of it's good
violence is definitely bad we should
strive to have societies with less
violence but I think that it is also an
expression of human energy and I think
we should have people of high energy in
society right for example I think that
you know this is also the reason why I
think that there are some very positive
developments in human history that have
at one point involved like you know
violent elements you can make a case
that certain kinds of social evolution
would have never happened without some
type of stuff either you know this
military stuff revolution stuff
organized religion you can argue that
these were instruments that are
necessary
perhaps still are necessary
for certain kind of transformations and
with regard to a soft reset it's very
interesting question oh it's a soft
collapse versus a hard collapse I
definitely don't think we will see a
very hard collapse in the case sense of
I don't expect a massive population
reduction I do expect some technological
stagnation and expect compounding
fragility then you can have something
that's very very fragile but stays for a
very very long time in phase transitions
right phase transitions between say you
know gaseous liquid solid forms maybe
even between plot plasma and and gaseous
forms I don't remember the physics quite
right there's a thing called a
metastable state in a metastable state
the material is already at the right
temperature to start say have water
start boiling but because there's no
disturbance to it it stays in the
previous transition and then if you drop
like a little speck into this kettle of
like you know metastable water it'll
instantly start boiling you start have
this massive amount of steam pump down
and I think societies when they become
stabilized or an active in this way I
think there are metastable state and it
can last there for centuries it's again
very similar to a dry forest hopefully
does this address some of the question
okay so let's go to WG would you like to
ask your question hi Sam oh thank you
very much I was just hoping you could
expand a little bit on the point about
what measures you do track you said you
don't follow direct measures like you
know violence because they could be
misleading and well they're worth
checking right but I think a lot of
people overplay the conclusions you can
reach from them
I was seeing a sacrum taking the social
conservative and I have to say say in
ancient Rome the the pagan it would be
the social conservative not the
Christian right the social conservative
critiques are often very subjective and
all who don't really account for their
being different setup so civilization
could have and then also
like a very narrow track of something
like violence it's really difficult to
define like almost I think almost
everyone who has said something
interesting about violence is actually
not quantified that they were actually
describing almost like a taxonomy of
when violence is is caused in the human
species right they were looking at cases
or types of violence or moods of
violence and that's more insightful okay
so the clarifying my position the police
oh yeah yeah thank you for thank you for
that um I'm actually you started to
answer the question that I had which was
what sort of measures do you actually
track well I had a restated I think
tracking population so saying that if
urban centers cease to grow and a
society is like very urbanized but it's
not increasing in population I think
that's an interesting sign that
something very basic has gone wrong if
you were to keep animals in captivity
and they consistently had a drop in
population that would suggest that
there's something really really wrong
with the captivity it's not clear what
it is I don't think the social
conservatives are right on this I don't
think the feminists are right on this I
think we just don't actually understand
what causes the human the human being to
reproduce or not but I would argue it's
probably very closely tied to something
like optimism and general well-being and
the belief that life is good but not
belief in a stated sense it's very easy
for a deeply unhappy person to say those
words it's you know much much more
implicit right so I would say yeah
population numbers are pretty good one
technology and ability to maintain
advanced technology right so in a way
I'm not gonna say complexity is good in
itself in fact complexity brings a lot
of problems and doubling down and
complexity can exacerbate those problems
there's some stuff by Tainter and so on
on these collapse dynamics only
necessarily going to those but it will
say sustained complexity is a good sign
that social differentiation is working
and that there are some functional
institutions left in a society and then
the third one might be and I do actually
think that
this one is again it's it's on the more
subjective side it's something like a
kind of material well-being that is
accessible now this might easily be
something that's unsustainable right
there are strong arguments to be made
that modern consumerist living was
unsustainable all along there are
arguments to be made that say in the
Roman Empire the excessive taxation of
the provinces it was is what enables the
prosperity of the a panini and peninsula
itself so modern-day Italy but I think
that all else equal you know this kind
of matching of ends means having the
material means available in a broad
swath of the population for the business
of life and for the business of creation
and so on that's that's a quite positive
sign so impoverishment all else equal is
a negative sign and again when I was
talking about the US I was implicitly
stating all three or perhaps at issue
right all three of these seem to be on
the negative side of that indicator if
the lights not read on the dashboard
it's at least orange okay Megan you have
a question so you're you're asking is
that what resource is it running out to
create these phenomena I've been
thinking of will as a resource or you
can say ideological direction so there's
a there's obviously very prominent
conflicts over voting not just like who
who we vote for but whether people vote
and that's a main conflict and I'm
wondering if that's also related to
directions and music and art and things
like that I think like for example
putting putting you know satanic symbols
into popular music I think that that
doesn't seem like just a coincidence to
me that's something that's really
prevalent that something to do with
taking people's ideological direction or
people's will as a resource whether
there's some interesting point there
about will will be
a resource that we're fighting over or
running out of maybe there's some way
you could take take that question in an
interesting direction
well first off let me just address one
of the claims you're making I don't
really know I've not looked at the music
industry I will say one shouldn't just
automatically dismiss of stuff as
conspiracy theories if one did one
completely missed that America's
founding fathers were freemasons and
that every revolution that you carry out
has to obviously have in the background
some real coordination it's not
spontaneous right for every revolution
there's a vanguard party it's only a
question who the vanguard party is or
was in France it was the Jacobin Club in
the Russian Revolution it was the
Bolsheviks and America was the founding
fathers but people don't really you know
they just think of them as Patriots
which is of course what happens if you
win so I would say that you know worth
looking into I don't have time for it I
don't have interest for it right now the
point however the bigger point that's
like less attention grabbing that I
think is a very good one is if will is a
resource right the ontology of
psychological phenomena is a very
difficult one
it actually takes a lot of like both
research thinking to establish
rigorously what we even mean when we
talk about mental phenomena try to
define memory it's actually really hard
try to define attention try to define
will it's hard to put into words and
even if you don't put it into words if
you try to embody it
people seem to embody different elements
of it so one possibility is that you
know humans are not the lens that can
see itself we just can't capture our own
psychology because if we try our
psychology just becomes more complex I
wouldn't go quite as far to say that the
art you know figuring out what will is
is impossible and I definitely believe
that even if we can't produce a
scientific account we can produce other
useful accounts of what's happening and
I do believe that there are resources in
the space of a sabbia as in the work of
you know the ancient scholar even cog
dune who wrote you know this fascinating
book on the cycle of desert life
city back to desert life where the
tribes out in the desert outside of the
cities developed fellow-feeling and
trust and therefore because they're
better coordinated even though they're
much much poorer than people living in
the city
they can easily overtake the city become
new elites however the children of these
desert nomads find themselves again in
the city quite wealthy but if you're in
the city your main competitor are other
rich city dwellers it's no longer you
know the harsh environment or the other
tribes so over time that goes away
that's a generational level but I think
you were also perhaps thinking something
more direct like morale in military
science it's look very very clear that
morale is an extremely important
resource so in the military sense morale
means something like this
this ability willingness to carry out
missions coordinated livability this
positive spirit in fact if you read all
the literature on it they don't have a
precise definition either and start
sounding an awful lot like we'll the
idea the two armies fighting is
primarily contests of willpower is
something that both like you know you
know each and strategist of Greece and
the ancient strategists of China agreed
on and today these terms like
psychological warfare suggest even
modern theorists agree with it so yeah I
think the deployment of something like
will and the fracturing of will against
each other is is real I think that there
are more subtle things also happening I
think I would for example describe hope
right hope versus nihilism we're deeply
felt justified hope seems to be one of
the most important preconditions for
human life where I would argue again
that you know and then is hope and will
the same thing well Meacham would say
yes I'm not sure I would say quite yes
but there's there stuff to discuss there
and if this is the resource that's
lacking then you would I'm just curious
amilia with a complex manglers concept
of a Faustian civilization you might
enjoy reading that because that proposed
you know the the legend the myth the
fast is you know strikes
a bargain basically with the devil you
know I will know all the secrets of the
world I will be immensely attractive
I'll experience every physical pleasure
and so on all it takes is my immortal
soul now at the end of the very end of
the story there's a loophole the person
gets out of the bargain but the analysis
is that perhaps Western civilization two
or three hundred years ago set its
course on this kind of Faustian bargain
and he contrast this with what he calls
the major in civilization where he takes
ancient Christianity and Islam could
actually part of the same civilization
with a completely different mindset and
before that I think he has the a colonic
civilization so there is definitely a
lot of very interesting theoretical work
on these topics and it's worth reading
and I would say that I don't get the
impression that 1960s America was
primarily driven by the least overt will
power so I don't think that's quite it
and it seems like World War two America
is not driven mostly by willpower
so again willpower can like be described
in other ways at least at least for the
u.s. I incline against this answer that
was that was fun does a great question
thank you great thank you
near on would you like to ask your
question so you mentioned earlier that
Americans should be paying attention to
internal Chinese politics just as much
as British people pay attention to
internal American politics but it
doesn't really seem to be something that
happens do you see that as like a lack
of demand are we just uninterested to
focus ourselves or do you see it as a
lack of access for journalists to
actually be able to get that information
back across those it's an excellent
question I think that I think that we
would do very well to just start
translating the documents that they put
out and examining them critically
because there's a massive massive amount
of documentation released by the Chinese
government and by everyday Chinese
citizens every day
we don't have enough educated Chinese
speakers who are also educated in
political science or focused
significantly on the Chinese system I
think that there is demand for now there
is demand to read about China I think if
our public discourse was a higher
quality there would be more demand to
read deeply on China it's actually
extremely important to understand both
strategic partners and strategic rivals
we could be reading at least as much in
detail about China as we are about
Europe I think there's at least that
much demand in say contemporary American
society and I say this is a European
right that only you know I've only lived
in the US or something like five years
and it seems to me there and that the
bottleneck is on the education side I
think there's just far too few people
that speak Chinese and there is far too
little of the initial organization I bet
if there was a magazine that focused on
translating articles from China and they
could get funding I bet they could make
a strong pitch if they had a few good
scholars and I think it would be cited
widely by outlets like you know I think
New York Times would cite them I think
you know the Atlantic would cite them I
think the national interests like
palladium whichever outlet you think
they would be very happy to have such
material so I think it's it's a it's a
it's a staffing problem I was just
considering that you know the very very
first Japanese state transatlantic visit
in I think the 1860s where the biggest
barrier was just finding enough people
in Japan who spoke English to go on a on
a steam boat and go all over the San
Francisco and see what America is like
right a few years after Commodore Perry
forcefully forced forced and can
humiliated Japan by forcing to trade now
in a lot of accounts this is presented
as completely reasonable I've written an
article on why actually trade as far
more ambiguous is not always positive
but I think that we are sort of like you
know maybe America should be like this
maybe we should send a steamboat over to
China and have onboard all the people
that can speak Chinese and have them
live in China for six months if the
Chinese government allows it and then
they can write to us what they see
I think there's we should be at least
that open to understanding the culture
thank you maybe grey would you like to
ask a question hi Sam oh so nice to see
you again this week I was really
lighting up when you were talking about
domestication and captivity and the way
that we don't really fully understand
why there's something wrong with it but
that we definitely know that there's a
lot of harm that comes from it so I
would just love to hear you say more
about what would be bad about fully
domesticating humanity yeah I mean again
it's an intuition to explore I think
that well perhaps for starters like
there's the observation that wild wolves
have about 30% more brain mass than
domesticated dogs so in other words I
bet the dogs are not thinking for
themselves as much as the wolves are and
I think that you know all of these in a
simplistic way the critique of imitation
or the critique of groupthink it's it's
a very strong critique right so I think
if we become overly domesticated we'll
be come to consensus oriented and we
will perhaps even as a whole species
miss important option so it's not good
from a survival perspective but then
from a driving perspective I think it's
bad because it suggests that full stop
we have less motivation to do things
right if you slow down a computer by 50%
and then say good news is computer lasts
twice as long I don't think you've
really done anything worth bragging
right it's sort of like a candle it's
burning more less brightly and it lasts
longer doesn't seem very useful so if
the answer is that you know see the
only way we can avoid this existential
risk to humanity is to just make us much
lower lower energy as individuals and
then the macro structure won't be put
under the kind of pressures that might
lead to you know nuclear war or the
wrong kind of technological advancements
in that case I'm sort of like now-now
don't slow it down right let's go let's
go boldly there and see what happens
awesome thanks so much okay so what's
the what's the question there with it
this is where their guard to energy
return on investment is this the
question that you would like to ask I
guess Sam oh you were talking several
you know the the sinusoidal ups and
downs of society accessibility yeah
possibility well it I mean it I I think
Bob da Bogdanov Don off is written
extensively on this Peter church and is
written about clio dynamics and things
of this they disagree on the details of
the models and of baforee exactly and
the quadric of if you know if the
quadrature of macroeconomic waves they
also propose that sort of sort of
structure right they all look at it from
a different perspective and a lens but
one of the entry on a more practical
numerical quantifiable level not so much
a cultural level Joseph Tainter in his
book the collapse of like societies
societies and then Thomas a Breton in
your yes they talk about this energy
return on investment so one of the
things that people are looking at is the
is for example looking at on the basis
of the club of Rome's the limits of
growth book that essentially when a
society when the cost of energy or in
this case fossil fuel in our industrial
economies when that starts it gets to it
you hit peak when you hit peak oil or
peak coal when it becomes more and more
expensive to extract
that source of energy from the ground
where it costs more to pull it out of
the ground than you actually get out of
it then the society starts tanking at
that point and we're I think it's like
2005 in some cases in some parts of the
world 2010 we were hitting peak coal
peak oil and this sort of stuff so I
think that's coming to play and also I
think another factor which is I mean to
witting that there's some relationship
to it but not very direct that in the
early 1970s there was another inflection
point which was it was the first time in
US history
after a hundred and fifty years that the
u.s. overcame its it's persistent labor
shortage which allowed for the citizenry
of the u.s. to have rising wages which
were kind of overcame all of the let's
say embedded inequities that were
embedded into the culture they could
essentially you know okay my life is
getting better for the majority at least
economically even though I'm suffering
from all this crap and and after the
1970s that ended so it allowed all those
problems to kind of come to the surface
and I'm gonna shut up and I'm wondering
actually a good exposition the key issue
here is that there are so many
confounding variables for the 1970s
right you have like you can propose that
it's the energy there are people who
propose it's the like replacement of the
currency system there are people who
propose that that's like when you know
the demographic crash starts hitting and
it actually society was always a ponzi
scheme and you needed societies that are
heavy on young people and like on old
people because old people are too
conservative and rigid and like I think
the return on energy investment is a
very good measure I don't think it's
what's happening right now partially
because there seem to be a lot of energy
sources that could be used that could
generate very good returns that aren't
like like we not we've not hit cheap oil
right more than us
crash and oil supply we've seen a crash
and oil demand and that's unusual right
that's very unusual I actually am very
sympathetic to this sort of basically
like a Club of Rome style of peak oil
arguments because they just seem to be
actually completely correct on the basis
of the fundamentals it's just that the
concrete projections haven't met what we
are seeing right now perhaps right now
we have some different kind of crisis
and then in the future or later in the
21st century we actually start running
into issues when we run out of you know
uranium and oil we don't seem to have
been running out of oil right now right
so there there have to be at least some
additional types of crises that are not
energy crises cool next question so I
have is the declining resource somehow
related to the proportion of life
players to dead players in a society I
think that it must be so this is one of
the reasons why I was actually fairly
sympathetic to the question that will
and also the question of domestication
and so on it could be that overly
domesticated humans actually just make
for very bad life players without some
sort of burst of energy and observation
you go to the lowest energy action the
lowest energy action is doing what you
have always been doing or what you've
been taught to do or what everyone else
around you is doing now of course the
vast majority of things you could do or
could try to innovate are worse than
what everyone's doing around you so
there's also like a local irrational
argument to be that way right but if no
one's doing it then you know not enough
experimentation and not enough learning
if you never do something outside the
norm you can't really know why the norm
is there now can you at least not on the
basis of personal experience perhaps on
the basis of wisdom of people you deeply
trust and that's important but I would
actually argue that if you want to dream
up a new social order or way of being
you actually have to live through a few
of them right you have to experience a
few of them
few people could object to me saying
that you know Joseph Smith had a
colorful life or if we take you know the
Prophet Muhammad that he had a colorful
life or that Jesus had a colorful life
and if they didn't have these unusual
lives where they were like you know
debating the religious scholars while
they were 12 or something right or you
know let's be generous like engaging in
what's basically sounds like a treasure
hunt scam they wouldn't have learned
things about human nature
they're just needed right or at least
the truths about human nature was alien
to the world which they lived in at the
time I'm against the positing this deep
psychological complexity where it's like
very difficult to be self-reflective and
that quite possibly impossible
the live player declined there might be
a consequence my own theories related to
great founder theory related to you know
sub components of empire Theory stuff
related to players stuff related to
traditions of knowledge I obviously
think that's like very explanatory and
very much worth pursuing but the
question I'm asking like doesn't really
rely on it and I'm open to other answers
this is not the first like a paradigm of
history I've gone into right I was
extremely interested in a Peter Turin's
work around 2014/2015 a lot of people
right now are giving him credit that he
got 20 20 right I'm not sure he did I
would I would say argued the 20 20 a the
unrest is unrevealing underlying
problems but the protest movement and
you know the demonstrations and so on
would not have been as big a deal had
the plague not struck and you know the
Corcovado crack Ovid is not downstream
of social effect it's a biological fact
I'm sure there are social effects that
were risk factors for Kogut evolving but
since I think it's Kovac driven I
actually think 2020 is a lucky guess on
on Turkey's part but I deeply respect
his work I think his Cleo Dynamics
project is an extremely interesting one
and before that I've also like you know
read all of these books on the Club of
Rome stuff and say the kind of stuff
that was popularized by Jared Diamond in
his book collapse
so you know I don't expect this to be my
final theory of the world right now on
it I would answer yes it's a qualified
yes I'd look like 60% probability on it
and then split the rest between some
other theories and undiscovered theories
thank you all right engine your
questions hey Sam
Eric Weinstein has this interesting
thing where he talks about medium male
income and since the 1970s how it
flatlines and I know you were riffing
about that I was wondering if you just
continued to elaborate like what do you
think changed because you have as you're
saying so many confounding variables do
you think there's an attractor behind
them all or yeah just kind of if you had
any thoughts around that yeah it's a
very it's an interesting and difficult
economic question because we can't
actually analyze wages just as economic
facts the reality is that having a job
is a deeply socially important action
perhaps the real tribalism bother
America is the tribalism of being
employed right I'm a member of this
community
I am judged by these behavioral
standards if my boss fires me for
misbehavior others will see this and
know that I'm a sketchy person like this
is definitely like the it plays such a
social regulatory role to say what do
you do what is your job it's perhaps not
relevant to say 5% of the population 10%
it's certainly relevant for 60% or 70%
of the population they feel defined by
their jobs right so when we say medium
income has stagnated you also have to
measure the income I think we should be
very skeptical of the inflation numbers
that were seen getting it's possible
inflation is far higher I think it's
also possible there was growth that was
not captured by the numbers let's
remember mainstream economic orthodoxy
in the 1990s was that there have been
such vast increases in productivity due
to the introduction of the internet and
so on that the old numbers are not
capturing at all and that the old easy
statistics used from the set 50 60 70 s
that are showing relatives that
are actually hiding the vast increases
in living standards this view
occasionally returns and I think it's
still love you that's basically believed
within Silicon Valley there are some
people in Silicon Valley who might
believe an alternate version were like
well you know the Internet's make
everything so much more productive that
we've automated away all the jobs and
now really the problem is that our
technology is so great that there's
nothing for anyone to do and we need to
transition from jobs to UVI the problem
is ubi is meaningless literally like you
you will not find meaning on ubi unless
you did a much more radical
reengineering the entire culture the
yangyang idea of give everyone a
thousand dollars every month without
providing them with an alternate primary
social identity that's not their work is
like it's not even a half done
revolution it's like it's like sort of
it's like taking the wheel or taking one
tire out of a driving car like maybe the
car can continue to drive on three
wheels maybe or maybe you're just gonna
crash it really bad right so I feel that
there's an interesting and contrarian
idea maybe something about the way jobs
are social roles for people necessitate
in the very concept of having a job a
certain level of inequality so what
happened in the seventies was the social
roles hit their limits and was simply
not possible to pay people more while
maintaining the social differentiation
that the jobs require so in order I'm
safe proposing that there's something
like inherently tied to economic
inequality that is needed to make the
roles of having a job fit each other
neatly and at hitting these limits you
know do you can't the economy bends to
make the culture fit so that would be
maybe my proposal there and it's it's
again that's that's more of a hypothesis
I would put like 20 percent 20 percent
weight on but definitely 20 percent it's
not like a two percent hypothesis Pat
Ryan and one of his dark stoas had this
argument that you're wondering about UB
I look at Saudi Arabia they base
tically have UVI here a Saudi Arabian
citizen and look what happens there and
they also refer back in the days of Rome
that when they get free crane said they
just in drank so well again I'm
not even saying that you know maybe
maybe it's even worse maybe they don't
even they don't even drink maybe
they're just depressed okay okay you
know much about Weinstein's like in
doubt growth obligations therein you
have any comments you don't mind also
explaining it to those who don't know
it's certainly worth watching i'm not
sure i'll be doing justice to eric's lot
i think he is very much worth watching
on this topic and googling it the claim
would be that our institutions were made
on the premise of growth so when you
enter one of our institutions be it an
educational institution an economic
institution you were given an entry
position and you are told look this
isn't forever
your subordinate right now and yes we're
kind of exploiting you but this is where
you learn the ropes and one day you're
gonna be like me this is a liar when
told to grad students today it was not a
lie when told to grad students in 1940
1940 a grad student could expect maybe
to be a professor today they're deluding
themselves if they expect to become a
professor right the ratio is so
obscurely like lopsided there's just
such an overproduction of them so what
happens if you have a society where
literally all the institutions have
these kind of embedded growth
obligations where they are promising you
you know it kind of sucks right now but
you're buying into the system that's
gonna have beautiful returns you're
gonna have a big retirement you're gonna
get promoted you know you go for this
education and so on like if the growth
stops you might actually have supreme
social problems in completely different
systems all hitting at the bat at the
same time now very happy to be corrected
by others but this is my again attempt i
encourage everyone to go check out eric
weinstein his interviews on the portal
are wonderful it's the one it's the
sure I really enjoy watching himself
very much recommended and I would also
make an explicit comparison here to
peter Turin's elite overproduction
thesis where i think actually what peter
church's thesis shines is if you apply
the theory of the overproduction it
actually fits to a tee what's happening
in the academic system and you get a
very similar prognosis to the one eric
weinstein would propose exists there and
then also i would you know mention
empire theory which is a subset of a
great founder theory where i also write
on a similar dynamic it's called
centralized declining Empire is the type
of society where I use Empire in the
technical sense not in the sense of like
the Roman Empire the British Empire for
just as own of coordination maybe I'll
change that terminology it was a little
bit game theory inspired but like right
now I think you have to be extremely
careful with how you name your method
your your pseudo theoretical concepts
right you have to be careful about that
and do you have a reaction to one since
theory do you disagree with them in any
meaningful ways what do you think he
misunderstands mmm this is a good
question um what's always very important
to talk to people who have very
developed theoretical frameworks and do
them justice if I significantly disagree
with Weinstein's probably I believe much
more in tacit knowledge so it's less
resource-based focus and view of the
economy but rather tacit knowledge
intellectual dark matter essentially and
the failure to transmit that knowledge
is being upstream of economic limits
right and he might view it more like no
it's the failure to discover new things
I'm like no no no I think we're even
forgetting how to do some of the old
things perhaps not where we have like
physical artifacts like this microphone
right not yet though sometimes you know
it took it took quite a while for the us
to figure out how to put a man into
space and arguably it wasn't the US but
a South African entrepreneur and the
social technology right the social
technology stuff I think might be
breaking and I also think not all of our
institutions were truly predicated on
the embedded growth obligation so there
might be a technical disagreement
between us what share our institution
have this feature great key would you
like to ask your question hi mo right
thank you for speaking to these topics
and my question isn't very well
articulated but I would think that the
growth aspect kind of plays into the
question um I wanted to ask you about
your observations on on violence um when
you previously were talking about like
energy as a resource or you know the
domestic occasion piece of it I just
wanted to ask you how you differentiate
or how you see differentiation between
like offensive violence and defensive
violence and how it's related to human
nature and ethical actions and culture
it's super difficult right it's super
difficult because you know it's there is
something in humanity there is something
in how we are that causes us to seek out
violence over and over again and we are
repulsed by it and we hate it but we
also love it otherwise our video games
wouldn't be as violent as they are our
movies wouldn't be as violent as they
are or Mis wouldn't be as violent as
they are right and I don't know exactly
how that works and I also think the
question of aggression it's always so
it's so convoluted there are we could
try to figure out in the primordial
sense who is the first mover of violence
but very soon those calculations become
so complicated that it's not clear it's
very useful to figure out who started it
right perhaps at one point we have to
like just look at us like look around
and be like okay this is like a bunch of
preschoolers like you know beating each
other up
I don't care who started it right it's a
planet of preschoolers right and we
could say stop but then like you know
you know if you have to lost him in a
classroom to make them stop I don't know
maybe they were maybe they were happier
out in the grass and in the trees with
all the bruises even if they were giving
each other those bruises
so I would say that there are some
interesting books on this I would
possibly recommend without fully
endorsing let me see if I can find it
like there's an anthropological book I
mean you know there the classical books
like henna rinse stuff on violence I
think that's like a very ideological one
there's the better name and angels of
our nature by Steven Pinker there's like
stuff you know on you know revolution
disobedience the pacifist sort of stuff
there is a particular book I'm thinking
of that I'm not able to find so I'm
gonna tweet a link later to that book
and endorse it and maybe since I think
you've been a regular I think I've seen
you to a few of these other ones if I
don't get it
today I'll you know drop the link and
just mention the book I have in mind
that's slipping my mind and like
recommended here in addition to the
other ones thank you that's really
helpful and appreciate it yeah so
Twitter oh look out for it
Thanks very welcome there's kind of
interest in the chat on in a comment
that Peter made a little bit back I
don't know if Peter you want to share
your comment and see what Santa thinks
of it
or I can do it too it's pretty if you
want to jump in you can but I'm just
gonna share it so he's talking about in
Japanese society how the reward seems to
be and maybe you can help engine energy
return on or the reward seems to be
prestige rather than like money itself
is that some kind of resource as well
but maybe we're losing or don't have as
much of in the u.s. well it's possible I
think that in the 1950s for example
right the salaries of the CEO class were
notably lower and company spirit was
notably higher you do realize that like
IBM in the 1930s people who just get
together and sing songs about the
beloved beloved president of IBM like
you can find this song it's like
actually like funny right and they would
have pictures of like the CEO of the
company like everywhere like today this
almost feels like you know is this kim
jeong-hoon or something no no this is
just what these big companies would like
so in such a world
well maybe the CEO doesn't require a
salary and doesn't require quite as much
because they're already getting paid in
status and you know maybe companies are
a little bit more like cults than they
would be today so you know Japan I think
is definitely an example of this you
dedicate yourself to it the company
become who takes care of you the salary
differential isn't great but the
deference differential is very great and
I think people can be motivated by
social goods at least as much as they
can be by material goods arguably a lot
of consumerism is now here's the
negative side of consumerism it's
wasteful it's like you know producing
substitute goods where you have these
material markers they're supposed to
bring you a happiness but they don't
here's the positive side of it humans
are so social that we just neglect
physical fundamentals all the time but
if you kind of convince us to fetishize
physical things we will take care of
even of physical things if only to have
physical things be a token of our social
games so if you make it so that like
nice fast car is a status
goldeneyes fast plane is a status symbol
then we will do such an unnatural thing
as to learn how to like build the car
and build the plumb so it could be that
if human nature is perhaps been like you
know maybe consumerism was like maybe it
was an over response and a doubling down
on actually something failing desires
not being projected properly where our
desire to engage with the physical world
was lessening and we tried to keep touch
with physical reality by fetishizing
objects and for a while this work but
now we've even lost touch with the
objects we don't want to even consume
anymore and it's not because we've all
become enlightened
but it's because we've like become even
more unenlightened you know maybe the
design of Karen or something could be an
interesting book about that like I don't
know awesome great
so we're wrapping up here at the top of
the hour are there any final words final
thoughts you want to leave us with yes I
did
ultimately promise I would talk
something about pre foundings and what I
would cite here is I certainly wouldn't
endorse all in every one of these
historical figures we all have issues
and they're often pursuing values that I
would disagree with and that many in our
society would disagree with but I would
consider the case of Justinian and
Eastern Roman Emperor who assembled the
team of the very greatest experts he
could find in all domains from
accounting to civil administration to
scholarship to law and to military
matters single-handedly turning around
the faith of the Eastern Roman Empire
right so the Greek dominated corner
Greek speaking part you know
reconquering southern Spain North Africa
and Italy back into the empire arguably
Rome didn't fell didn't fall until
Constantinople was gone like that's an
example of individual impact another
case I would say is that you know
there's the refounding of Charlemagne in
his era where undoubtedly he reforms
what's basically a tribal structure and
changes it into a proper feudal
structure now again tribal versus feudal
I think today people aren't very deeply
sympathize
either of those but the fact is that was
a new civilization new society built and
created out of this ruins of an old one
and then finally I would also give
Augustus and again the reason I'm
sticking to Western history isn't
because seat ramses ii would be super
good to talk about or some chinese
emperor wouldn't be a great person to
talk about but it's because these are
our cultural touchstones right people
might know of justinian of the Eastern
Roman Empire they might know Charlemagne
and they might know of the Emperor
Augustus the Republic was in terminal
decline we can see it as a tragedy that
the Republic was dissolved by by that
point the Republic you know the cure was
worse than the disease the Republic was
set up to correct a terrible and corrupt
monarchy in ancient Rome and then the
Augustine dictatorship this Imperial
position of the princess the first
citizen was set up to correct for a
corrupt in decaying Republic so one
could argue that both what progress
right
both fix what was broken and fixed what
was essentially a tyrannical and
extremely violent system and when you
look at the lead emissions and pollution
is a tricky sign but I think the Romans
did not invest much in clean energy so
I'm just gonna take lead in the
atmosphere in ancient Roman times as
preserved in the gas bubbles in a
slander Gaius is a good indicator of
Roman economic productivity and have
something quite unfavorable like how
much led do you mind if we take that as
an indicator LED product you know
atmospheric LED went up this means
economic activity went up civil wars
ended for significant period of time see
the urban populations increased I think
he just did an amazing job of arresting
what could have been a terminal decline
for that civilization right Rome might
have been a 600 year civilization
instead of a thousand-year civilization
if it wasn't for him and again the key
note here would be all these people did
assemble very competent teams of
individuals around them right
Charlemagne like sponsored the
reintroduction of Latin education in the
territories that he ruled he
sponsored scholarships and even though
he didn't learn how to read himself was
a great sponsor of those just thinking
Reform the legal code as the Charlemagne
and to a lesser extent Augustus they all
changed military structures and people
missed when someone reforms the military
they never just reformed the military
they perform all of society think of
every time you were asked to respect the
troops that's a social technology right
we can pretend that the structure of the
US military doesn't profoundly shaped
American society and you know for that
matter things like policing and so on so
you know try to find the exceptional
people in the world you don't have to be
so megalomaniac to think you or want
them and try to help them okay that's
where I would leave it up for today
great thank you so much Sam out and
looking forward to what you bring for us
next week okay yeah I'm just gonna tell
us about some upcoming sessions we have
here at the stoah we have two upcoming
sessions that are really about getting
into difficult conversation and
controversy
the first one is tomorrow emotional dojo
with Kyra Kroger that's at 3:00 p.m.
Eastern Time and then we also the
following day have a dangerous space
with Ariel Friedman and that's at 12
p.m. Eastern Time
so I join us for those events I'm also
hosting Socratic speed-dating tomorrow
so come join me at 7:00 p.m. to have
some socializing and we see the stoah as
a gift and if you feel inspired to give
a gift in return you can go ahead and
visit us at the stoah that's the a slash
gift and you can provide a gift for Sam
Oh for me for any of the facilitators
here at the store we have some in the
room here today so if you feel so
inspired please go ahead and visit us up
that link and thank you all for being
here today look forward to seeing you in
the future